{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Wesley Osmus was drowned by the losing side in this battle. Victory in this battle was made possible by the cracking of the JN-25 code, completed with a ruse regarding water purification systems. William Halsey’s illness forced Raymond Spruance to take command during this battle, in which four Japanese aircraft carriers were sunk. For ten points, name this 1942 battle near a namesake atoll, often identified as a turning point in the Pacific theater.",
      "answer": "Battle of Midway"
    },
    {
      "question": "In this film, Brad Kane and Lea Salonga sing a duet that won an Oscar for Best Original Song. After marketing disputes, Dan Castellaneta replaced one voice actor in this film’s first sequel. Thirty percent of respondents to a December 2015 PPP poll supported bombing Agrabah, this movie’s setting, where Jafar seeks a magic lamp. Robin Williams voiced the Genie in, for ten points, what 1992 Disney film adapted from The Arabian Nights?",
      "answer": "Aladdin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This river is crossed by the John Frost Bridge, which replaced a structure fought over in the Battle of Arnhem during Operation Market Garden. For many years, the Roman Empire’s Germanic frontier began at the Danube and this river, which also forms Liechtenstein’s western border. For ten points, name this longest river entirely within Western Europe, which flows from the Alps through Germany to the North Sea.",
      "answer": "Rhine River or Rijn River"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man converted to his religion after listening to the preaching of Thomas Loe. This man wrote Innocency with Her Open Face, which led him to be imprisoned in the Tower of London, where he wrote No Cross, No Crown. This man signed a treaty with the Lenape tribe, granting him land for a colony governed by his Frame of Government. For ten points, name this Quaker who founded an American colony and its city of Philadelphia.",
      "answer": "William Penn"
    },
    {
      "question": "The world’s first openly lesbian prime minister was elected in this country, which saw the Kitchenware Revolution after all three of its largest banks collapsed in the aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis. This nation’s Althing is the world’s oldest existing parliamentary institution. Massive air travel disruptions across Europe resulted from the 2010 eruption of the Eyjafjallajokull [EYE-a-fyat-la-yo-kutl] volcano in this country. For ten points, name this Scandinavian island nation whose capital is Reykjavik.",
      "answer": "Iceland"
    },
    {
      "question": "This empire defeated Linghu Chao’s rebels in its successful defense of Yongqiu [yong-chu]. Huang Chao’s rebels against this dynasty slaughtered tens of thousands of foreigners in Guangzhou in 878. This dynasty’s power was interrupted by Wu Zetian’s brief Second Zhou Dynasty and by the An Lushan rebellion. Emperor Gaozufounded, forten points, whatChinese dynasty thatpreceded the Song Dynasty?",
      "answer": "Tang dynasty"
    },
    {
      "question": "Charles Michelson, the head of the DNC, coined the term for these settlements in 1931, and a reservoir where Central Park’s Great Lawn would be built was home to one of the most prominent of these locations. One of these locations in Anacostia Flats was cleared out by Douglas MacArthur to remove the Bonus Army from Washington, D.C. in 1932. For ten points, name these shantytowns formed during the Great Depression, which were named for the predecessor to Franklin Roosevelt.",
      "answer": "Hoovervilles"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man started the Informbiro period after his country was expelled from the Cominform in 1948 after feuding with Joseph Stalin, and this leader was the only European who helped create the Non-AlignedMovement, servingasitsfirstSecretary-General. Thisman’scountry consistedofsixsocialist republics including Slovenia, Croatia, and Serbia. For ten points, name this longtime Communist ruler of Yugoslavia.",
      "answer": "Josip Tito"
    },
    {
      "question": "An empire situated in this modern day country was overthrown by the Sosso people after taking its capital at Koumbi Saleh. This country was home to the Ashanti Kingdom and is the birthplace of Kofi Annan. This was the first sub-Saharan African country to gain independence from a colonial power. Kwame Nkrumah led, for ten points, what country formerly known as the Gold Coast with capital Accra?",
      "answer": "Ghana"
    },
    {
      "question": "The election of Daniel O’Connell led this man to pass the 1829 Catholic Relief Act. This man became Governor of Seringapatam after winning in the Fourth Anglo-Mysore War, and he later led forces at the Battle of Salamanca during the Peninsular War. Along with Gebhard von Blucher, this man won a battle that ended one French emperor’s return to power. For ten points, name this British general who won over Napoleon at Waterloo.",
      "answer": [
        "Duke of Wellington",
        "Arthur Wellsley",
        "Arthur Wesley"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s most honored armed force was chosen by Gorgidas and included 150 pairs of men. Epaminondas led this city to victory at Leuctra, but was killed in victory at Mantinea. Twenty-seven years later, this city lost at the Battle of Chaeronea, where this army was defeated by Philip II of Macedon. For ten points, name this leader of the Boeotian Confederacy, a central Greek city legendarily founded by Cadmus.",
        "answer": "Thebes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This term names the elite force of 150 pairs of Theban soldiers. Plutarch’s account of this force notes that each pair of soldiers were lovers.",
        "answer": "Sacred Band"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One philosopher born in this nation was the lover of Alexander Berkman, the attempted assassin of Henry Clay Frick. The pamphlet “What Is To Be Done” supported the establishment of a “vanguard” to ferment revolution in this country. That pamphlet was written by an author from this country who traveled from Switzerland in a sealed boxcar and delivered the April Theses upon his return to Petrograd. For ten points, name this home country of Emma Goldman and Vladimir Lenin.",
        "answer": [
          "Russia",
          "USSR",
          "Soviet Union"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This assassin claimed inspiration from Emma Goldman to commit his most infamous deed; she was briefly arrested, then tried to prevent this man’s execution on October 29, 1901.",
        "answer": "Leon Czolgosz"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s commander, Hudhayfah ibn Mihsan, assisted his campaign against apostasy known as the Ridda Wars. After hundreds of hafizes were killed at the Battle of Yamama, this ruler, called “the Truthful,” ordered the collection of the verses of the Qu’ran. For ten points, name this companion of Muhammad who directly succeeded him as the first of the “rightly guided” caliphs.",
        "answer": "Abu Bakr or Abdullah ibn Abi Quhafa"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A hafiz is a Muslim who has completed this task, necessary for preservation of the Qur’an prior to Abu Bakr’s work.",
        "answer": "memorize the entire Qur’an"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While attacking American cannons in this battle, Robert Abercromby told his troops “Push on, my brave boys.” At the end of this battle, Charles O’Hara attempted to surrender to the Comte de Rochambeau, but was directed to Benjamin Lincoln instead. One side in this battle attempted to retreat from Gloucester Point. British losses at this battle led to the Treaty of Paris. For ten points, name this defeat for General Cornwallis, the final major battle of the American Revolution.",
        "answer": [
          "Siege of Yorktown",
          "Battle of Yorktown"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "British efforts to reinforce Yorktown were ended after Thomas Graves lost to the Comte de Grasse in this naval engagement.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of the Chesapeake",
          "Battle of Virginia Capes"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The zarzuela was invented in this country and named for its royal palace. In this country, Bach’s Chaconne was transcribed by Andres Segovia, a master of the classical guitar. Miles Davis’ Sketches of this country include a selection from Concierto de Aranjuez [con-thee-AIR-toe d’ar-ahn-WETH] by Joaquin [wah-KEEN] Rodrigo. For ten points, name this Iberian country where Isaac Alb´eniz wrote works like Cadiz, Granada, and Catalun˜a.",
        "answer": "Spain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Flamenco music was developed in this Spanish region, an autonomous community where the Alhambra was built in Granada.",
        "answer": "Andalusia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man left his job after his employer was seduced by 80 dancing girls. This philosopher argued that words must be made to fit reality through a process of “rectification of names,” and his Five Relationships included ones between father and son and brother to brother. This man, who served under the Prince of Lu, believed in cultivating a trait known as “ren”. For ten points, name this Chinese philosopher, the author of the Analects.",
        "answer": [
          "Confucius",
          "Kong Zi"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Qin dynasty ended a period in Chinese philosophy that purportedly contained “this many” Schools of Thought. Mao Zedong later asked for this many flowers to bloom before crushing that campaign with the Anti-Rightist Movement.",
        "answer": [
          "100",
          "Hundred Schools of Thought",
          "Hundred Flowers Campaign"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Three brothers and a sister legendarily founded this city by two mountains and a river, and Hilarion was proclaimed as this city’s Metropolitan by one of its rulers, nicknamed “the Wise”. Nestor chronicled the history of this city in his Primary Chronicle, and this city was founded at the intersection of the Desna and the Dnieper Rivers. A Rurikid line that ruled this city was started by Vladimir the Great, whose son, Yaroslav the Wise, continued this city’s tradition of Christianity. For ten points, name this city, the medieval home of the Rus people and the modern capital of Ukraine.",
        "answer": [
          "Kiev",
          "Kievan Rus"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Prince Oleg moved the capital of the Rus from this city, his home, to Kiev. As Prince, Yaroslav the Wise briefly united Kiev with this city.",
        "answer": "Veliky Novgorod or Novgorod the Great"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man vowed to never travel by train again after suffering an injured leg in the Hightstown rail accident with John Quincy Adams. Gideon Welles initially refused this man’s donation of his largest personal steamship to the Union Fleet, and this owner of the Staten Island Ferry feuded with James Fisk and Jay Gould over his railroad empire. For ten points, name this 19th century American, known as “Commodore” for his extensive transportation empire, whose philanthropy founded a university in Tennessee.",
        "answer": "Cornelius Vanderbilt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Vanderbilt captained the ship at the center of this Supreme Court case, which held that Congress’s power over interstate commerce extended to navigation.",
        "answer": [
          "Gibbons v. Ogden",
          "either"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Battles on American Soil",
      "prompt": "In which American battle did...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "the “Shot Heard ‘Round the World” start the American Revolution?",
          "answer": "Battle of Lexington and Concord"
        },
        {
          "question": "a general supposedly say “Don’t fire until you see the whites of their eyes!” on Breed’s Hill?",
          "answer": "Battle of Bunker Hill"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sitting Bull’s Sioux forces cause the death of George Custer?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Little Bighorn",
            "Battle of the Greasy Grass"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "heavy casualties in Miller’s Cornfield lead to the bloodiest single-day battle in American history?",
          "answer": "Battle of Antietam or Battle of Sharpsburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "P.G.T. Beauregard surprise Grant’s forces near Pittsburg Landing?",
          "answer": "Battle of Shiloh"
        },
        {
          "question": "Isaac Brock and Tecumseh force the surrender of a fort in the Michigan Territory?",
          "answer": "Siege of Detroit"
        },
        {
          "question": "Daniel Morgan defeat the British, led by Banastre Tarleton, in a South Carolina grazing land?",
          "answer": "Battle of Cowpens"
        },
        {
          "question": "Pancho Villa’s Division of the North raid a New Mexico town, triggering Pershing’s expedition?",
          "answer": "Battle or Raid of Columbus"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Versailles",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Sun King who moved the court to Versailles.",
          "answer": "Louis XIV"
        },
        {
          "question": "war ended by the Treaty of Versailles.",
          "answer": "World War I"
        },
        {
          "question": "glassy hall where the Treaty of Versailles was signed.",
          "answer": "Hall of Mirrors or Galerie des Glaces"
        },
        {
          "question": "economist who attended the Versailles talks and wrote The Economic Consequences of the Peace.",
          "answer": "John Maynard Keynes"
        },
        {
          "question": "queen who received the Petit Trianon chateau at Versailles as a gift – hers to enjoy before she was executed.",
          "answer": "Marie Antoinette"
        },
        {
          "question": "Parisian royal residence replaced by Versailles, whose gardens later became a public park.",
          "answer": "Tuileries Palace or Tuileries Gardens"
        },
        {
          "question": "aristocratic political system whose excesses led to the building of Versailles and the French Revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "Ancien Regime or Old Regime",
            "Bourbon Dynasty"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "room requested by Louis-Philippe to commemorate France’s millitary?",
          "answer": "Hall of Battles or Galerie des Batallies"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Cuba",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "disease caused by HIV, for which Cuba has the lowest rate in the Caribbean.",
          "answer": "AIDS or acquired immune deficiency syndrome"
        },
        {
          "question": "tobacco commodity, of which John F. Kennedy purchased over a thousand prior to signing an embargo in 1962.",
          "answer": "cigars"
        },
        {
          "question": "failed 1961 coup, led by the CIA-backed Brigade 2506.",
          "answer": "Bay of Pigs Invasion or Playa Giron"
        },
        {
          "question": "Argentinian revolutionary whose militia helped Castro succeed in the 1959 Cuban Revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "Ernesto Che Guevara",
            "either"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "leader who was overthrown in the 1959 Cuban Revolution.",
          "answer": "Fulgencio Batista Zald´ıvar"
        },
        {
          "question": "1901 bill that limited Cuba’s self-rule after the Spanish-American War.",
          "answer": "Platt Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "1980 mass emigration of Cubans to Florida.",
          "answer": "Mariel boatlift"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor General of Cuba during the Spanish-American War, nicknamed “Butcher.”",
          "answer": "Valeriano Weyler y Nicolau"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An 1883 Convention for the protection of intellectual property was signed in this city and is still in effect. The Confederation of the Rhine was initially convened in this city. A series of post-World War I treaties reinforcing the (20 pts)",
        "boundaries of defeated nations including the Treaties of Sevres, Trianon, and (10 pts)",
        "Neuilly-sur-Seine were signed in this city, which was also the site of treaties ending the Spanish-American War and the Revolutionary War. For ten points, name this city, the namesake of many treaties and the capital of France."
      ],
      "answer": "Paris"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This organization’s former director, Keith Alexander, dismissed claims that it held “millions of dossiers on people.” This organization was able to collect 30 days’ worth of (20 pts)",
        "phone calls from entire countries, such as the Bahamas, via its MYSTIC program; that program’s existence, like that of (10 pts)",
        "PRISM, was revealed by Edward Snowden. For ten points, name this American intelligence agency that, unlike the CIA, focuses on monitoring electronic communications."
      ],
      "answer": "National Security Agency or NSA"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1624, Fyodor Kotov described the dismantling of this group’s capital, Sarai. One ruler of this group defeated Mamai at the battle of Kalka River; that man, Tokhtamysh, united the (20 pts)",
        "White and Blue sections of this group into a single force. Uzbek Khan was the longest-reigning ruler of this army, which split off from the (10 pts)",
        "Mongol empire after the death of Genghis Khan. For ten points, name this Mongol army, either named for their wealth or for the color of their tents."
      ],
      "answer": "Golden Horde"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This President responded to the “Capitol Crawl” by signing a civil rights law that required reasonable accommodations in the workplace. He promoted volunteerism with his “thousand points of light” speech and defeated a (20 pts)",
        "Democratic opponent with an ad featuring escaped convict Willie Horton. This man’s re-election bid was (10 pts)",
        "hampered by the failed pledge, “Read my lips: no new taxes.” for ten points, name this 41st U.S. President who defeated Michael Dukakis in 1988 and fathered the 43rd U.S. President."
      ],
      "answer": "George Herbert Walker Bush"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One side moored their ships at the Dog’s Tail during this battle, and the eventual victors entrenched near a grove sacred to Heracles. The city of (20 pts)",
        "Eretria had been sacked prior to this battle, where the victors were joined by a small force of Plataeans. The Carneia prevented the arrival of a (10 pts)",
        "Spartan army to this battle, where the victors accidentally used a double envelopment after thinning out their center to defeat Datis and Artaphernes. Miltiades defeated the invasion of Darius I in, for ten points, what battle, after which Pheideppides ran 26 miles to bring news of victory over the Persians to Athens."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Marathon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Wolfgang Capito and Martin Bucer invited this man to minister to French refugees in Strasbourg. At the Synod of Dort, the Arminians broke with this man’s followers. This predecessor of Theodore Beza ordered Michael (20 pts)",
        "Servetus burned at the stake for heresy. His faith is often summarized in “five points,” including limited atonement and total depravity, which were first laid out in his (10 pts)",
        "Institutes of the Christian Religion. For ten points, name this Protestant theologian who took power in Geneva, Switzerland, and whose followers believe in predestination."
      ],
      "answer": "John Calvin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William Borden accused this man of being a Soviet agent in a letter sent to J. Edgar Hoover. This friend of Richard Tolman and teacher of George Volkoff noted that stars of a certain mass could not become (20 pts)",
        "neutron stars. During the Trinity test, this scientist noted that he had (10 pts)",
        "“become Death, the destroyer of worlds,” a month before his creation was used in Japan. For ten points, name this leader of the Manhattan Project and father of the atomic bomb."
      ],
      "answer": "J. Robert Oppenheimer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a political cartoon, one of these organizations is told, “by the Great Eternal, I’ll cleave thee to the earth!” by a man wielding a cane labeled “Veto.” State, rather than federal, charters established the (20 pts)",
        "“wildcat” type of these institutions, some of which were called “pets,” as they were given excess federal (10 pts)",
        "money. Until Andrew Jackson’s intervention, Nicholas Biddle led, for ten points, what type of financial institution that, in the 19th century, issued their own currency?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "banks",
        "the Second Bank of the United States"
      ]
    }
  ]
}